

SENIOR SOFTWARE DEVELOPER
m.utku.k@gmail.com
+1 (650) 546-9756
SAN FRANCISCO / CA
HTTPS://UTKUKARATAS.COM

#### # PROFILE

I'm a polyglot developer. I've been a tech-lead / backend architect for the most of my career. Since 2015 my main area of interest has been JavaScript - which led me into frontend roles too - which makes me a well rounded full-stack developer productive at both high and low levels of system design with a product focus.

My main area of expertise lies in JavaScript and Python ecosystems on Unixy platforms. I've been involved in JVM world in recent years. In a previous life I was doing desktop app development via Delphi/C++.

I have managed small to mid size teams before; however these days I refrain from management roles - unless it's a hands-on management role - I do not enjoy it as much as coding and I'd like to go deeper on my favorite technical topics: modern DB technologies, large scale data processing, and distributed computing. Extended edition of my past experience below can be found at <a href="https://utkukaratas.com/resume">https://utkukaratas.com/resume</a>.

## **# EXPERIENCE**

- SENIOR SOFTWARE DEVELOPER; HAZELCAST

2020Q4-PRESENT

Hazelcast is the leading open source in-memory data grid in JVM world. Being part of the RD & Cloud team I'm building and maintaining management & monitoring applications of Hazelcast ecosystem, helping to integrate existing applications into the Cloud Paas solution of the company.

Technical work mostly consists of Java, Spring, Typescript/React + Docker/Kubernetes as the orchestrator.

- FULL STACK DEVELOPER; STEALTH STARTUP

2019Q4-2020Q3

Led the team of 3 on mobile platforms via React Native. Also helped backend infrastructure team scaling with ScyllaDB modeling & scaling terabytes of daily throughput.

Technical work mostly consisted of Typescript/React Native, Node.js, Postgresql, ScyllaDB.

- CONTRACT DEVELOPER; WHIPDATA

2018Q2 - 2019Q4

Led the frontend at Whipdata - an Amazon marketplace analytics platform. Vue/Nuxt/Node was our choice of framework/platform.

Also helped the backend team architecting/scaling the system with Django/Postgresql.

- CONTRACT DEVELOPER; ZEBRAMO

2017Q1 - 2018Q2

Built the web application of Zebramo app. from scratch. This was a large scale consumer facing PWA consuming Zebramo's backend services tailored for its existing mobile app.

Built the internal marketing tool akin to Customer.io; letting the Zebramo team execute marketing scenarios based on customer behaviours, all scriptable via a web based diagramming environment.

Under the same umbrella, built a sister web application in a related vertical, architected backend & frontend from the design stage to production.

Technical works above consisted of Python/Django/Wagtail CMS backed by Postgresql and Redis; as for the frontend stack Vue/Nuxt.js, JointJS, <u>segment.io</u> were chosen.

Helped Wizbu bootstrap several mobile projects. Wizbu was a software agency mainly involved in IOT and E-commerce verticals.

Technical work mostly consisted of React Native and Swift.

### - CONTRACT DEVELOPER; ASOSYALSOZLUK

2015Q2 - 2016Q4

Built a social media application from the ground up with a team of 3.

Technical work consisted mainly of Python, Django, TypeScript, XMPP, LXD on the backend. On the frontend side the tech stack was Vue.js and React-Native. Later in product's lifecycle, frontend stack has migrated to React/Next.js.

## - CTO/CO-FOUNDER; YCEO/EKSERIYA

2012Q2 - 2015Q2

Built a team of ~10 making mobile/desktop games. Served as the CEO and CTO. Hired and worked closely with multiple groups of software engineers, designers and 3D artists.

Technical work consisted mainly of C++, OpenGL, Javascript, HTML5 and mobile SDK's of IOS and Android. Managed a team of 6 graphic designers and modelers.

# - CTO; YCEO/TACIRNET

2010Q - 2012Q2

Architected and built a Python based E-commerce platform akin to Shopify. Served as the first CTO. Grew a team of ~20. Technical work consisting of Python, Django, Redis, Postgresql.

Under the same umbrella company I also took a part of a team building an Intranet Application for TCDD (Turkish National Railways) enabling TCDD to track their wagons more precisely via GPS. Worked closely with the engineering team designing kinetic energy powered GPS hardware, integrating the hardware with our custom on-premise infrastructure. Technical work mainly consisted of Python, PHP, Postgresql, OpenLayers.

# - SOFTWARE DEVELOPER; PFAIDE

2009 - 2010

Designed and built a shareware Python IDE for Windows platforms.

The work mainly consisting of Delphi, Python, C, Win32. Open sourced the result after a shareware flop.

# - SOFTWARE DEVELOPER; MORFIK TECHNOLOGIES

2006 - 2008

Helped integrating Morfik's backend platform port to Linux using FreePascal. Morfik was a Web 2.0 IDE solution and a platform generating Web Apps from Pascal / Visual Basic code bases (a la Delphi for Web 2.0).

Technical work mainly consisted of Object Pascal on Linux.

# **# EDUCATION**

Sakarya Universitesi, Sakarya 2003 - 2008, Physics - dropped out.

Kadikoy Anadolu Lisesi, Istanbul - 1998 - 2002

# # PERSONAL

Languages: English, Turkish.

Born 1983, Male.